If you have taken term insurance or you are about to take it, then
a small mistake that you make
in your proposal form, today a small mistake will result in the
family's claim worth crores being rejected and the
insurance company will not give the claim in future because these are red flags
which you need to know.  So there are some
red flags in the proposal form which
we need to know before buying a term
insurance and even if we have already bought it, it is
important to know that whatever mistake has been done should be
rectified.  So
what do I mean by red flag?  That such things where
your chances of claim rejection will
increase significantly.  So in the video
we will talk in detail about the three red flags
that you should not do at all.
[Music]
Quick reminder before we start the video,
if you haven't subscribed to our channel, please do so.
So that
you get the right information at the right
time.  Let's move on to the video.  What are the
three red flags in term insurance
that you need to identify and
avoid making these mistakes?  First,
write half-truths in propositional form.  There is
a very big column in the proposal form for medical
history or medical declaration.
It has to be filled very carefully and very slowly.  We take a
declaration about your good health.  First let us take a declaration about whether you were taking any medicines.
You have to
give information about any past hospitalization you have.  You have to give information about any past
surgery you have undergone.
You have undergone some treatment
in the past which has been cured but it is
necessary to give information about it
in the medical form.  So, on the
basis of medical information, whether your policy is accepted
or loading is levied or not,
it happens on the basis of medical underwriting.
You know there are two
types of underwriting in term insurance.  In financial
underwriting, your income is checked and on
that basis you are given a policy.   The
second is medical underwriting.
You are given a policy on the basis of your health.
So in medical underwriting, if the medical
disclosure form is incomplete or wrong
information is filled.  If half the installment is filled then the
insurance company will not pay the claim.  The
family will suffer losses in the future.  For
example, if you take BP tablets or
BP medicine, then it
is important to inform the insurance company.  no forget.
Or many people say that I used to take it earlier but
now I don't take it.  But you have blood pressure.   When
you said this, the doctor refused to
take it.  But you have to
tell that also to the insurance company and write it in the form.
So you take thyroid medicine, diabetes
medicine or any other small
medicine or any small
treatment has been done in the past.  If there is any
surgical history, someone
was hospitalized for two-three days, someone underwent treatment and
then recovered, then it
is necessary to tell all these details to the insurance company in the
proposal form.  It is necessary to give that.  So if you do
n't give it, it's a red flag.   The
insurance company will reject the claim.   The
family will not get the term insurance claim for the purpose for which you are taking the term insurance.  I
read a very interesting quote.  Honesty is the
cheapest premium you will pay.  Quite an
interesting quote.  Think about it.  The
second red flag is the mismatch between your income and sum
insured.  Meaning your income says
that your sum insured should have been this much.
But if you misrepresent the income.  If
your
income is written incorrectly, your sum insured will
depend on it.  This also means that
suppose your income is Rs 10 lakh.  You were
eligible.  I am assuming
₹1 crore.  You had already taken a policy of Rs 50 lakh
from somewhere else.  So you did
not disclose this company and
took a policy of Rs 1 crore from here.  So there is a mismatch between sum assured
and income.  According to your income,
your eligibility was Rs 1 crore.
But now you are insured for Rs 1.5 crore.
So the financial underwriting failed
here.  There will be no problem now.
But in future, when the claims are settled, the
claims of both the companies will be settled cumulatively.
There you will face the challenge that your
eligibility was not being met.
How did you get the cover?  So,
whenever you are going to buy new term insurance, it is important to tell about your old policies,
any LIC policy you have taken, any
policy that is running.
So this is the next red flag where the
claim policy can be rejected.   The
best thing is that you tell everything about the
old policies you have taken, even if they are worth Rs 1 lakh,
2 lakh or 5 lakh,
to the insurance company.  Provide your ITR
copies so that the insurer can verify them himself.
You should not face any problem tomorrow because you did not
tell me.  Provide your ITR copies.  Let the
insurance company verify.  If
they give you cover on that basis then it will become even simpler.  There will be no
problem for your family.
Third red flag: Be sure to tell the
insurance company about your lifestyle.
As you
know, there are two types of premiums in term insurance –
smoker and non-
smoker.  So due to some reason smokers become
non-smokers.  Suppose you
are a smoker and you take the policy as a non-smoker.
And if any early claim comes or it is
proved in any claim that you
were a smoker, then the insurance company will not
give the claim to the family.  It is a question worth crores.  You have to
pay a premium of ₹10.00 right now.  But
when the family has to get money because the
financial life of the family and the future of the family
depends on it.  The company will
not pay the claim.  So it
is very important to tell about lifestyle habits.  Such as smoking,
alcohol.  Your job is a high risk job.  Still it
is important to tell.  With LETS you
work in the mining coal industry.   If
you are in the Merchant Navy, then it is important to inform the
insurance company about your job profile
because the premium is
charged on that basis.  If you have a high
risk job then the premium will be higher.  So, it
is important for the insurance company to know your lifestyle habits.
Many times it also happens that you say that
I used to smoke earlier, now I don't smoke.
You should also tell that to the insurance company.
They will test it.  You can ask for proof of that.  There are
some tests, advanced
tests, they will do those tests.  We will
give you the policy on that basis.  So don't hide from your side.
Do not give wrong information in order to save Rs 4000 or Rs 10,000 premium.  What will
happen with that?  Now only two to four thousand will be saved.  But
the purpose for which you have taken the policy is that my
family should get the claim.  If you don't get that then there
is no point.  There
is no benefit in taking the policy.  So avoid these three red flags.
You should go and check immediately.  If
you have taken a term insurance policy, then have
you made these three mistakes?
Open your proposal form,
open your policy document and check whether
everything is well disclosed or not.
To conclude, the three red flags
we talked about.  First,
show honesty in your health details.  Secondly, there should not be a mismatch between your income and sum
assured.  Thirdly,
lifestyle details should be properly mentioned
in the proper policy form.  So the
proposal form is very important.
And check in the policy document.  Whatever is
written in the proposal form, has it been included
in the policy document or not?  If it does not
arrive, immediately mail the insurance company.
Otherwise the whole purpose will be defeated.
I have seen claims getting rejected because
of wrong proposal forms filled.
I am telling you this from my 20 years of experience.  it happens.
So you must be
worry-free that I took term insurance.
Everything is fine now.  But there are still
red flags in that.  Those are the red flags you have to check.
Go check it out and comment.
Apart from this, if you feel that there
is any other red flag or any other point to be kept in
mind, please tell us that also.  Other
people will also benefit from it.  If you
found the video useful, please don't
forget to subscribe.  So that you keep getting more such informative videos
and don't
forget to share them with your friends and family. Those who
take the proposal form very casually and
give it to someone else to fill it, be it an
agent or a relative, do not pay attention, then it is
important to pay attention.  So this is what I
wanted to share with you.  Thank you so
much for watching our video.  Stay safe, take
care.  See you in the next video on a new topic.